The coral gravel that sleeps under the sea of sand,
砂の底に眠る礫珊瑚も
or the carpets with gold and silver interwoven,
金銀を織り交ぜた絨毯も
or the rainbow-colored honey that can only be eaten by the people in heaven,
天上人の食す虹色の蜜も
there is nothing I need among them.
何もいらない…
We only want what you have given us.
私たちが手に残すものは　あなたがくれたもの…
We are the halves of the soul, that will never be apart.
私たちは永久に離れることのない　魂の半身
With the purist tears in our eyes, let us wait for the moment when we can eventually see each other.
今は至純の涙だけ抱いて　ともに見える時を待とう
July 20, 93 S.S.
砂刑暦93年　7月20日
We had a joint funeral at the beard square.
ヒゲ広場にて合同砂葬
Hakuji-sama and the people of mud whale are flowed to the sand.
砂に送られるのは　ハクジ様や泥クジラの民
As well as the enemy soldiers died in the battle with us.
そして　戦死した敵の兵士もいた
Bye bye!
バイバーイ
Sienna... Tell me why...
シエナ…　どうしてなの
Why did you choose to suicide?
自ら死を選ぶなんて…
Captain, see her face for the last time please.
団長さん　最後に顔を見てあげてください
Her hair...
髪を…
Cut a piece of Sienna's hair, and leave it to me.
シエナの髪を一房切って　残しておいておくれ
Why don't you see her off? She is your wife!
自分の妻なのに　どうして見送ってあげないの？
Who are you...
誰だ　お前は…
Whose tear is it...
この涙は　誰の…
What's a pity, Shuan.
哀れだよ　シュアン…
We may save the apatheia without hearts, but no one can save you.
心をとられた兵士の方が　まだ救いがあるってもんさ…
You are so cold, my mother.
冷たいなァ…　「母さん」は…
See your face...
その顔…
at the sea yourself.
水鏡に写してごらんよ…
It's like the demon is laughing.
悪霊が笑ってるように見えるよ
Demon... Yeah.
悪霊…ね
Huh...Hahaha...
フッ…はははは…
Hahaha!
はっはっはっはっは！
Translator
字 幕 入 力
ssnake
ssnake
静寂よ　旋律よ　儚き印よ
静寂よ　旋律よ　儚き印よ
Timing
字 幕 編 集
zwc1991
zwc1991
砂上にこの地に　生き続けたのなら
砂上にこの地に　生き続けたのなら
罪を纏う世界から　鯨の歌を聴いた...
罪を纏う世界から　鯨の歌を聴いた…
運命を　感情を　抱くべき子たちよ
運命を　感情を　抱くべき子たちよ
さ  き
さ  き
その先へ　その未来へ
その先へ　その未来へ
導かれたのなら
導かれたのなら
幾千の声　空想の地へ
幾千の声　空想の地へ
舵を切って行こうとした
舵を切って行こうとした
バラード
バラード
幾千の声　砂の海の譚歌
幾千の声　砂の海の譚歌
After the attack from skulax,
スキロスの襲撃のあと
We were trying to regain our everyday lives step by step.
人々は　ゆっくりと日常を取り戻そうとしていた
Ne...
ネ…
Hey!
コラーッ！
Why are you here?
なにしに来た
I made some galenicals.
薬を作ってきました
It is the nutrient to extend the short lives of Shirushi,
もともと　「印」の短命を治そうと思って
that I have been researching on.
研究していた栄養剤なんです
Please let him drink it after he wake up.
目を覚ましたら　飲ませてあげてください
It's your fault.
…あんたのせいだ
Cuz you have chosen Oni into the assault team,
あんたがオウニを突撃隊に選んだりしたから
he got into...
こんな事に…
And Nibi...
ニビも…
I am sorry.
ごめんなさい
I made you feel sad.
悲しい思いをさせてしまった
S... Stop it!
は…　はなせよ！
Please let me promise.
約束させてください
I will never, make anybody fight anymore.
もう　誰も戦わない
Nobody will fight.
…戦わせない
Since now we have known Oni has the power to destroy a Nous,
…オウニにヌースを破壊できる力があると分かった今
somebody may persuade us on starting a war.
誰かがまた戦争をすると言うかもしれない
But there will be victims for each battle.
でも戦うたびに犠牲者が出る
There will be people hurt.
誰かが傷つく
Therefore I am thinking about a peaceful way.
だから私は　戦わない方法を考えます
I will protect everyone next time.
今度は私が　皆を守る
Kids, say thank you to Oni.
さあみんな　オウニにお礼を言いましょう
Thank you, Oni.
ありがとう　オウニ
You helped the mud whale.
泥クジラは助かったよ
The nutrient juice by Suo is bitter, but drink it.
スオウの栄養ジュース苦いけど飲んでね
We will bring you more presents when you wake up.
起きたらまたプレゼントいっぱい持ってくるね
Also thank you, Kicha!
キチャにもありがとう
Suo, the presbyters are calling you.
スオウ　長老たちが呼んでるの
The presbyters?
長老たちが？
Yeah.
ええ
What?
ん？
Lykos?
リコス？
After they withdrew from the mud whale,
泥クジラから撤退したあと
how are the soldiers been?
兵士たちはどうしたのかしら？
They should have returned to the mother ship.
彼らは母艦に戻ったはずです
sentikinesis
サイミア
However, the power of lifeboats is the thymia of soldiers.
ただ　避難艇の動力は兵士たちの情念動なので
I wonder if they have enough stamina to get back to the mother ship...
彼らの体力が母艦までもったかどうか…
They may be exhausted...?
力尽きたかもしれない？
Yeah...
ええ…
Hey! Stop it!
わっ！　よせよ
Shhh!
し〜！
Won't the mother ship attack us?
その母艦が攻めてくることはないのか？
I believe they won't in the meanwhile.
しばらくはないと思います
How do you know?
なぜ分かる？
νοῦς
νοῦς
Because Nous is an indispensable defense to prevent the invasion from other countries.
他国の侵攻を防ぐためにも　ヌースは不可欠な存在だから
σκύλος
σκύλος
The lost of Skulax the Nous for the empire,
今回　帝国がヌース･スキロスを失ったことは
will become an significant blunder of my brother,
φάλαινα
ἐκκλησία
エクレシア
Without the approval of the Emperor and the supreme chairman of the Soul Church,
皇帝陛下や魂召会最高議長の承認なしに
νοῦς
νοῦς
it is impossible to dispatch a ship with a Nous.
ヌースを艦載した船を使えるとは思えない
So it is sure to say we are safe for the time being, right?
当分は安心だと思っていいのね
Perhaps.
おそらく
But it is just my prediction, and I am just a soldier.
でも　これは一兵卒だった私の予測にすぎません…
I can hardly believe my brother will obey the punishment.
兄が　このままおとなしく処分を受けるとは思えない…
Masuo, have you got up?
マソオ　起きてるか？
Yo, old guy.
おう　おっさん
What the hell you are here, I just get slept.
なんだよ　せっかく寝てたのに
It's omasa bamboo alcohol.
オオマサゴチクの酒だ
Alcohol?
酒？
But I'm just a shirushi. Can I drink it?
「印」の俺が飲んでいいのか？
I thought it is banned because we may lose our controls of thymia.
サイミアが暴走するかもってんで禁止なはずだろ？
Ah, it means you are no longer worrying about that...
まあ　その心配もなくなったってことか…
It is prepared by Shinono.
…シノノさんが用意してくれた
By her...
…そうか…
Then, I'll drink it without hesitation.
じゃあ　遠慮なく
See you.
じゃあな
Oh, wait!
あ　待てよ
Have a drink with me.
お前も一杯つきあってくれ
Ah... No!
あ…　ダメ！
ολιβίνης
これはオリヴィニスがくれた大事なものだよ
Oh...
わっ！
What?
うわ！
It's an animal?
生き物だったの？
It's food?
くいものだったの？
Ah!
あっ！
We can no longer eat it if it runs away!
逃げたら食えなくなる！
We can't eat it!
あの子は食べちゃダメ！
What's that?
なんだ　こいつは！
Hey! Don't run away!
こら！　逃げるな！
Chakuro!
チャクロ！
You guys have eavesdropped?
あなたたち　立ち聞きを？
κόκαλο
κόκαλο
Hey, Kókkalo!
こら！　コカロ！
Kókkalo? Is that Kókkalo?
コカロ？　あれが？
We are sincerely sorry!
失礼しました〜！
Hey!
こらあ〜っ！
Hey, how can you drink that fast.
おい　そんな一気に飲んでどうする
Don't be angry...
おこるなよぉ…
Why are you being so cold...
なんでそんなつめたいんだよぉ…
Kucchi...
クッチー…
Who's Kucchi!
誰がクッチーだ！
I'm worrying about you, Kucchi!
おれ　クッチーのことしんぱいなんだよぉ〜
You must be lonely if I died!
俺が死んだらさみしいだろ〜
I don't need your worry, you muscle brain.
お前みたいな脳キンに心配されるいわれはない！
That's it!
そうだな！
Well, after all,
まあ…　結局のところ
we have to accept what's going to happen.
なるようにしかならないしな
Well, what's wrong with you...
もう…　なんなんだよおまえは…
After all the sadness, the people of mud whale still
つらい出来事を乗り越え泥クジラの人々は
believed that they could get back to their everyday lives.
日常が戻ってくると信じて疑っていなかった
No, they were hoping that.
いや　願っていた
Oh, our master is finally back home.
おやおや　主がやっとお帰りだ
What's up? Don't be hesitate.
どうした？　遠慮することはない
They are my precious pierrots.
皆　私の大事な道化だ
Oh my god, he is bringing a girl home.
あらやだね　この人女を連れ込んだよ
He worth our esteem.
スミに置けないねえ
Even me, was a playboy in the past.
わしだって　昔は鳴らしたもんだ
You liar!
ウソばっかり！
What?
は？
It's not a lie! The only thing I have changed...
ウソじゃない　変わったのは…
is my head!
頭だけさ〜
What's up?
…どうした？
ἐκκλησία
ἐκκλησία
The inquest by the Soul Church will soon be undertaken.
まもなく　エクレシアによる審問が行われるはずです
It is not the time for laughing...
笑ってる場合では…
It's fine.
大丈夫だ
I have already had the strategy in my head.
もう頭の中に入っている
In your head?
頭の中？
This guy is planing to do that again.
またやるつもりだよ　この人は
His story is the greatest in the world.
物語らせたら天下一品だからねえ…
Shut up!
うるさいっ！
Your laughs as well as the voices of your castrated pierrots
あんたの笑い声も道化どもの金切り声も
are provoking me!
癇に障るんだよォ…！
It seems he is in a mood because he failed to make friends with us.
仲間外れでご機嫌ななめらしい
Ah...
あっ…
Is it... a dog?
犬…　ですか？
It's not dog.
犬じゃない
It's a lion.
「獅子」だ
You are the guy on Skulax...
あなた　スキロスに乗ってた…
I added you into the list of death by error.
私…戦死リストに加えてしまいました
Don't mind.
かまわない
It's better treat him as dead.
死んだことにしておいた方がいい…
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
When is... the next attack to Fallaina?
ファレナは…次の襲撃はいつになった？
I have to go Fallaina!
ファレナに行かなきゃ！
There is nothing else that can make me happy!
もう　他に楽しい事なんて…
There is only one way.
方法が一つだけある
Become my pierrot.
私の道化になる事だ
λιοντάρι
λιοντάρι
Ryotari.
リョダリ
What?
え？
You must be kidding...
冗談だろ…
How can I... become a fucking pierrot...
オレがそんな…　道化なんかに…
I can bring you to the war if you are my personal belonging.
私の私物ならば作戦に同行できる
It's the only way.
もう　方法はそれしかない
No... No way...
い…　いやだ…
I hate that!
いやだそんな事…
How can I become a fucking pierrot!
オレが道化なんて
It's bad to say fucking pierrot!
“なんて”ってひどいなァ…
Be easy, it's fun.
大丈夫　楽しいヨ
You should fit it.
オマエ　きっと向いてる
Isn't this good? It just fit you!
これなんかどうだろう　お前にぴったりだ
In the mud whale, we depends on the rains to get water supply.
泥クジラの生活水は雨に頼っている
It was said that the river of the heaven
池で水遊びをしていると
will flow down if we play water in the pond.
天の大河があふれて落ちてくる　という言い伝えがあったため
So we went playing water if it did not rain for a while.
人々はしばらく雨が降らないと　水遊びを行った
What a waste!
もったいない！
What?
は？
What are you doing, Ginshu?
なにするの　ギンシュさん
Don't cry!
涙だよ
We are lacking of water, bear it!
水不足なんだからガマンしろ！
It hurts!
いったあ〜
After all, the tears will be accumulated in the pond, why can't I cry?
どうせ涙だって　池に貯まるんだからいいじゃない
Ah, you're right.
あ　そっか
What are you doing there?
なにしてるの？
I'm crying to increase the water here!
泣いて池の水を増やすんだよ！
Hey, you should also cry!
ほら　お前たちも泣け！
People can smile again, soon after the sorrow.
悲しみのあとでも人は　また笑うことができる
Why do people have such an unstable and uncertain
こんな不安定で不確かな感情というものが
feeling called emotion?
なぜ人には　あるんだろう？
Suo-sama, don't your fingers hurt?
スオウさま　おてて　いたい？
You are clenching your fingers too much!
指組みしすぎちゃだめ！
Hey, if you are not acting happily, there won't be rains!
ね　楽しそうにしてないと雨降らないよ
...You are right.
…そうですね
What?
ん？
Don't say enemies are coming again!
まさか　また敵が？
No, that's not the ship of the empire.
違う　あれは帝国の船じゃない
So it's from another country?
まさか　別の国？
...The crest of blue hourglass?
…青い砂時計の紋章？
If they can be our friends,
味方ができれば
it is possible to help everyone without war.
戦いを避けみんなを助ける事ができる
What the hell the milk smelling!
なんだか乳臭いっ！
There is indeed a sweet smell like milk.
たしかにミルクみたいな甘い香りがしますね
But be careful, Roharito-sama.
ですが　ロハリトさま　ご用心を
It is an unknown island that we have never seen in our country.
本国がこれまで遭遇したことのない
No!
わっ！
It hurts...
あいたたた…
Welcome to the mud whale.
ようこそ　泥クジラへ
My name is Suo. I am the chief here.
わたくし　首長のスオウと申します
Did you get across the sea of sand and come here?
砂の海を渡ってこられたのですか？
Are you OK, Foni?
大丈夫か　フォニ
Are you OK?
大丈夫ですか？
May I help you?
何か　お手伝いできることは…
Wha..wha..what a beautiful nudist!
びびび　美形の裸族が！
How can the sturdy female warriors Gígantas be like this!
屈強な女戦士ギガンダ姉妹がなんたるザマだ
I am the son of the Duke of Amonlogia of the United Kingdom of Sidelasia.
余は　スィデラシア連合王国アモンロギア公領領主が息子
Roharito Anastenagmós Neje-Immiskin Emarica Antipater Nor Amonlogia.
ロハリト･アナステナグモス･ネイエ＝イミスキン･エマリカ･アンティパトロス･ノ･アモンロギア
is my name!
で･あ･る！
Too long!
長い…！
Dear Roharito Anastenagmós Neje-Immiskin Emarica Antipater Nor Amonlogia.
ロハリト･アナステナグモス･ネイエ＝イミスキン･エマリカ･アンティパトロス･ノ･アモンロギアさま…
Glad to see you!
はじめまして
He remembered!
覚えたっ！
There can't be any rudeness even as little as a single sand grain during the first meet!
ファーストコンタクトは
I think you said you're the chief here.
首長と申したな
Yes!
はい！
Then prepare the welcome party for us as soon as possible,
それでは　直ちに余のもてなしの準備をせよ
the chief of nudists.
裸族の長よ
Nu...dists?
らぞく？
Wha wha wha what have I done!
どどどどうしよう…
It is as rude as a tank of sand!
これでは桶いっぱいの砂よりも失礼だ…
Don't be ashamed, the chief of nudists!
恥じることはないぞ　裸族の長！
I don't care about the differences in culture.
余は文化の違いなぞ気にせぬ
Huh?
え…？
I will accept you as you are!
ありのままのそなたらを認めてやろう！
Nezu, what's happening?
ネズ　どうなってる？
I will do my best to help you make your lives modern and cultural.
そなたらが高度で文化的な暮らしができるよう
Immediately finish the procedure for make this island under my administration.
ただちに　この島が余の支配下に入るための手続きを行う
And claim the handover of all your rights to me.
全権力の譲渡を命じる
What are you talking about?
…なにをおっしゃっているのですか？
Didn't you just say,
あなたは先ほど　私たちを
you will accept us as an equal?
対等の存在だと認めてくださったはずではないのですか？
Suocchi!
スオっち！
You can't, Ginshu!
いけない　ギンシュ！
You will make it a war again!
また戦争になってしまう！
How can I be equal with you?
余とそなたらのどこが対等なのだ？
You are the monkeys that can do nothing!
なにもできぬ猿が
I will show you ignorant guys the power of Restraingun with our country's prides.
無知なるそなたたちに
Well...
やれやれ…
Captain!
団長さん！
With such a small number of people who seems to be unable to use thymia,
人数も少ないサイミアも使えそうにない
how can you be as conceit as that.
そのくせ物騒な奴らなんて
We should just seize them.
捕らえてしまえばすむことでしょうに
Roharito-sama,
ロハリトさま
it is impossible to deal with that number.
この数では　敵いません
Please surrender to them.
降伏を申し出てください
Ganva, what did you say?
ガンヴァよ　何を申す？
Why do I have to surrender to them!
なぜ余が降伏せねばならぬのだ
Because you are the master of us.
あなたが皆の主人だからです
Ehh...
ぐ…
Are you hungry?
おなかが減っているのですか？
How poor you are.
かわいそうに
Let me prepare your meals right away!
すぐに食事の用意をしましょう
Tasteless!!!
まずい！
Tasteless tasteless tasteless tasteless tasteless tasteless!
まずいまずいまずいまずいまずいまずい！
It is as rich as the best milk and has a fruity fragrance...
上質なミルクのようなコクにフルーティーな香り…
It is the first time I have eaten such a tasteless food~~~!
こんなにまずいものを食ったのは初めてだ〜！
Call the head chef here!
料理長を呼べっ！
Huh? You mean the children who boiled this?
え？　茹でたのは子供たちですが？
What? You just boiled it?
なに？　茹でただけ？
There are so many bamboos you can pick in the groves in the center of this island.
島の中央の竹林でたくさん採れるんです
I see.
なるほど
The bamboo shoots are the reason why this island smells like milk.
この島が乳臭いのはこの竹の子のせいなのか…
I want it!
欲しい！
I will take this back to Amonlogia!
余は　これをアモンロギアへ持ち帰る！
But the freshness is the most important for bamboo shoots...
ですが　竹の子は鮮度が大事で…
Of course,
もちろん
I will take back the whole groves!
竹林を持ち帰るのだ！
And the whole island!
この島ごとな！
What?
はあ？
What is that fucking guy talking about?
なにを言ってるんだ　コイツ
Excuse me.
じゃない
What are you talking about, my dear guest?
何をおっしゃっているのです　お客様
Be quick! Let's move this island!
さあ　早く　この島を動かすのだ
Make it heads to Amonlogia!
アモンロギアへ向かわせよ！
What the hell are you talking about?
なにを言ってるんだ　アンタ
Excuse me.
じゃない
What the fucking stupid things have you just said, my dear guest?
何をお馬鹿な事を言っておいでなのです　お客様
Our mud whale has been wandering without control for decades.
この泥クジラは何十年も前から
Nobody knows where we are going.
誰にも行き先は分からない
Move it? Head to somewhere?
それを動かす？　向かわせる？
If we could make it, we weren't suffering that much!
そんな事できれば苦労はないんだ！
Lykos?
リコス？
I wanna be alone for a while.
少し一人になりたいの…
Lykos... She is strange since the guests came.
リコス…お客さんが来てから様子がおかしい
I wonder if she became homesick.
まさか　帰りたくなったとか？
No no no!
ないないないよ！
κόκαλο
κόκαλο
Kókkalo!
コカロ！
Emma!
エマ！
Great! I've been looking for you.
よかった！　ずっと探していたんだ
I wanna ask you about this puppy.
君にその子の事聞こうと思って
I got it from a girl named Olivines I met on Skulax.
スキロスで会ったオリヴィニスって子からもらったんだ
So you are the one who got it?
これ　あんたがもらったの？
Ah... Yeah...
あ…　うん…
You are really great...
…やっぱ　あんたは最高だわ…
...I didn't mean I'll give it to you.
…君にあげるんじゃない
I wanna ask you what it is.
その子がなんなのか教えてほしいんだ
You have told me that
戦いが終わったら
after the war you will tell me the secret of Fallaina, right?
ファレナの秘密を教えてくれるって言ってたよね？
Fine. As a reward...
…いいわ…　ごほうびよ…
κόκαλο
コカロ
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
Fallaina will go on a new journey after getting the bone.
骨を得て　ファレナは新しい旅に出るわ
What this puppy is, and the story of Fallaina and sinners,
この子が何なのかも　ファレナと罪人の物語も
I will show you all of them...
全部見せてあげる…
κόκαλο
κόκαλο
Kókkalo!
コカロ！
Wings...
…翼…
Emma... What's going on... What's it?
エマ…　どうなってるの…　これ？
The mud whale is steered?
泥クジラが舵を切ってる？
Didn't you think it's strange?
おかしいと思わなかった？
Both Lykos' ship and the battleship Skulax
リコスの船も　戦艦スキロスも
νοῦς
νοῦς
can moving towards a destination if they have nous on board.
ヌースを乗せた船は行き先を決めて動いていたわ…
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
But Fallaina wasn't able.
でも　ファレナは　そうじゃない
Because Fallaina was a prison of exile, one part of it has been deprived.
ファレナは流刑の檻だから奪われていたのよ
The rudder...
“舵”を…
κόκαλο
κόκαλο
νοῦς
νοῦς
The bone is exactly the rudder for ships with nous.
コカロは　ヌースの船の“舵”なの…
Steer yourselves from now on.
あとは　みんなで舵取りをしなさい
Cuz life is a fight.
命は戦いなの
Living, seizing, and burning yourselves.
生きて　奪って　自分を燃やすのよ
In that night, we people on the mud whale had a dream.
その夜泥クジラの民たちは夢を見た
A little girl came to our beds and got into our ears.
小さな少女が寝床へやってきて耳の中へ入ってしまうのだ
The girl sang a magical song in our heads.
少女は頭の中で不思議な歌を歌い
And acted as if she was praying.
祈りの仕草をした
That was so sad that we all cried, and waked up.
それが　なんだか悲しくて泣いてしまい　目を覚ますのだが
And the girl came out as a drop of tear,
少女は涙の粒になって出てきて
faded away from the windows...
窓の外に消えていった…
乾いた海の跡　望んで
乾いた海の跡　望んで
I will draw the other side I have never seen
まだ見ぬ対岸を描く
囚われの心のままなら
囚われの心のままなら
You may live without knowing the pain
こんな傷みも知らずにいた
The one who told the beautiful story
美しい詞を告げたひと
Can not wait for the dawn
夜明けも待たずに
Until beyond the end of world, I am swimming
果てのその先を泳ぐ
Listen to the insects' song
虫の唄
That night is our memory
眠らず君と聞いた記憶
Just link hand in hand
手を　ただ結んで
No matter it is twilight or a distant country
半色でも　遠い国でも
短い一章に生まれた夢を
短い一章に生まれた夢を
But let us go and embrace that dream
抱きしめに行こう